Leo Hurwitz collection, 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991
George Eastman Museum
- Series 2, Papers, 1910-1992; 1925-1991
  - Subseries 2, Personal, 1922-1991; 1925-1991
    - no title (Box C088)
      - Correspondence 1985-86, current, 1984-1986 (Folder 34)
        Personal and professional correspondence, including letters regarding Hurwitz's participation as a panelist, film festival judge, peer reviewer, and academic referee, and inquiries regarding Hurwitz's films for duplicating and festival exhibition. Correspondents include Robert E. Hart; Bill Nichols; Mare Dore; Marion Michelle; Naomi Rosenblum (regarding the Paul Strand Archive); Jane Dudley (regarding the end of their marriage); Johan van der Keuken; Marie and Walter Briehl; Thomas Donley; Robert Hurwitz (includes wedding photos); Max Blatt; and Midwest Distributors. Also includes invoices, a published interview with Hurwitz by Dan Nissen (in Dutch); and a note to Abe [no last name given] alluding to an "episode at my home." In English and German.
    - no title (Box C089)
      - Swedish, Scandin. seminars, 1983; 1986 (Folder 40)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's 1986 trip to Scandinavia. Includes a brochure from the Dramatiska Institutet/Swedish Dramatic Institute in Stockholm; program calendar for the Orion theater at the Finnish Film Archive; Swedish press clipping regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed/Samtal med Peggy[Conversations with Peggy]; Folkets Bio film magazine, featuring an article on Hurwitz; two "Shoot Film, Not people" [working title for Dialogue with a Woman Departed] postcards; letters from Nelly Burlington; Hurwitz's handwritten notes; and maps of Helsinki, Copenhagen, and Danish tourism materials. In Swedish, Finnish, Danish, and English.
      - Helsinki seminars etc. 3/31-4/9/89, 1988-1989 (Folder 49)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's 1989 participation in the Documentary Project of the Finnish Film Foundation. Includes Finnish newspaper articles about Hurwitz, with English translations; project program; program calendars for the Orion Theater at the Finnish Film Archive; business cards and contact information; hand-written notes; correspondence; and black-and-white photographs, including several of Hurwitz. In Finnish and English.
    - no title (Box C090)
      - [Bag labeled: Important files as of 9/15/77], 1975-1977 (Folder 3)
        Professional correspondence primarily regarding film screenings and grants. Also includes some personal and family papers, including the will of Adolph Cook Glassgold and Sophia Delza.
      - [Bag labeled: 1979 check books (LH) plus assorted stuff], 1963; 1971-1980; undated (Folder 5)
        Personal and professional correspondence, including letters regarding the settling of Peggy Lawson's estate. Other items include general research materials, print orders, and programs. Contrary to the folder title there are no checkbooks. Material is in English and German.
      - [Bag Labeled: Misc. incl: Portugal trip '82, Eleuthera '84, mail], 1980-1984 (Folder 7)
        Includes materials related to Hurwitz's trips to Portugal and the Bahamas, including bills, receipts, hotel and travel information, and foreign currencies. Also includes color photographs and personal and professional correspondence. In English and Portuguese.
    - no title (Box C092)
      - Mail to be sifted, 1980-1982 (Folder 10)
        Letters, postcards, holiday cards, and other largely personal correspondence. Includes a note from Emile de Antonio and photocopies of file pages, possibly from de Antonio's FBI file.
      - 1981 -- Mail to be sifted (mostly Europe), 1981-1982 (Folder 15)
    - no title (Box C094)
      - [Personal correspondence and documents, clippings, notes], 1968-1976; 1982/1983; 1989; undated (Folder 5)
      - [Correspondence -- personal and professional/notes, living expenses], 1968; 1969 (Folder 9)
        Personal correspondence from Jane Dudley and Marie Briehl, professional correspondence from Gordon Hitchens and the Directors Guild of America, living expenses/budget, and notes on location of film elements and storage invoice.
      - Hospital bills to be settled (P.L.H.), 1971 (Folder 10)
        Correspondence regarding Peggy Lawson's medical bills and death, including letters from the Motion Picture Film Editors Local 771 union, condolences, and a request for documents.
      - [Professional correspondence, distribution reports, passport application], 1970-1972 (Folder 11)
        Correspondence from Gordon Hitchens at Film Comment;Strange Victory and Haiku distribution reports; and Hurwitz's passport application.
      - [Melkweg Cinema correspondence, Joris Ivens telegram], 1983 (Folder 17)
        Correspondence announcing that the Melkweg (Milkyway) Cinema was awarding Hurwitz the Award for Reality Research. Also includes a telegram from Joris Ivens (in Dutch).
      - Hold/then file, 1976-1981; 1991 (Folder 18)
        Professional correspondence related to rights, speaking engagements, and draft of a letter promoting a film by Manfred Kirchheimer. Also includes print inspection notes for This Island, correspondence on funding, screening flyers, and personal correspondence.
      - [Personal correspondence, speaking engagement notices,Dialogue with a Woman Departed promotional material], 1970; 1982 (Folder 23)
        Includes legal correspondence regarding Hurwitz's divorce from Jane Dudley; a New York University mailing; production notes and flyers for Dialogue with a Woman Departed; flyers for Hurwitz's speaking engagements; notes regarding This Island; and a clipping about Hurwitz.
      - Dean's report 1970-71, 1969-1973 (Folder 24)
        Material related to the New York University's (NYU) Dean's Report, including thoughts about the school and a letter from Hurwitz to NYU students. Also includes material related to a car crash; jury duty; Hurwitz's divorce from Jane Dudley; AFI publications; seminar ideas; and outline for a film not by Hurwitz.
    - no title (Box C096)
      - [Correspondence, photograph negative], 1963-1964 (Folder 1)
        Includes correspondence from the Screen Directors International Guild, a Film Comment survey, personal bills, National Educational Television (NET) tax and reimbursement information, and a photographic negative sent by Charles Pratt.
      - [Envelope labeled: Jane's letters from Israel], 1965-1968 (Folder 10)
        Letters from Jane Dudley and others. Also includes correspondence regarding a special screening of Native Land for Paul Robeson's birthday and a television broadcast of The Museum and the Fury; automobile documents; correspondence from VEB DEFA [East Germany] regarding Hurwitz's submission of films; and membership cards from the New York Public Library and the Screen Directors International Guild.
      - [File Pocket labeled: Hollywood --Here at the Waters' Edge and "The Scarlet Letter"], 1962-1963 (Folder 18)
      - Misc. -- Hollywood, 1963 (Folder 18e)
        A response to Here at the Waters' Edge; notes titled "Science and Superstition"; business cards; and personal correspondence from Peggy Lawson in a manila envelope.
    - no title (Box C097)
      - [Bundle of letters labeled: Desk 11/73], 1968-1972 (Folder 5)
        Personal, family, and professional correspondence, including undated draft of letter to be sent on behalf of Columbia Concerned Parents regarding the 1968 student protests at Columbia University; Eric Reiner regarding the Institute of Film and TV at New York University; letters from Jane Dudley, Marie Briehl, and Deborah Dickson; letters regarding the American Documentary Symposium held at Brandeis University; Hurwitz family meeting minutes; unsigned letter of agreement to Lionel Rogosin/Impact Films regarding distribution of Native Land.
    - no title (Box C098)
      - [Personal correspondence and notes, mailings, distribution report], 1965-1973 (Folder 2)
        Includes issues of Art Now: New York magazine with a cover letter from the editor; prospectus for "Vision of a City" by Hilary Harris; correspondence from Jane Dudley; a clipping regarding National Educational Television; research notes on divorce; a Strange Victory distribution report; and professional correspondence.
      - [Personal correspondence and notes, mailings, distribution report], 1965-1973 (Folder 2)
      - [Swedish Seminar -- preparatory material, clippings, notes], 1987 (Folder 5)
        Materials related to preparations for Hurwitz's seminar on Art and Film held at the Swedish Dramatic Institute, Stockholm, including notes on films to take; list of participants; program; copies of 1974 and 1975 notes on Dialogue with a Woman Departed; and correspondence. Also includes Swedish newspaper clippings; personal correspondence; and bars of music titled "'Leo's Spine' (Peggy's Theme)." In Swedish and English.
      - [Correspondence on John Brown project, Rolfe letters], 1989 (Folder 3c)
        Correspondence regarding John Brown project and Edwin Rolfe letters. Also includes a copy of a 1947 letter Joe Freeman wrote to his psychiatrist about his relationship with Jay Leyda.
    - no title (Box C099)
      - [Correspondence], 1976-1980; 1989 (Folder 2a)
        Personal and professional correspondence, including holiday cards; insurance policies; film revenue reports; and requests for interviews, film loans, and letters of recommendation. Correspondents include Susan Dodge Peters at George Eastman House with a questionnaire regarding Elizabeth McCausland; Eleanor Burlingham; William Alexander; Russell Campbell; Directors Guild of America; Trudy Kraft; Peter Hawley; Cook Glassgold (with a sketch for a TV short titled "The Renoir Snatch"); Thomas Brandon (writing to former members of the Film and Photo League regarding Bill Nichols' and Russell Campbell's "libelous" assertion that the League was Soviet funded); Manfred Kirchheimer (with New York Times clipping about CBS News collaborating with the C.I.A.); Stanley Salfas; John H. Lawson; the White House (regarding the accident at the Three Mile Island nuclear facility); Darrell Random; the Middle East Film Festival; the John Solomon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation; Grand Valley State Colleges (including a copy of the issue of The Paper devoted to Hurwitz); Vivienne Silver (with a copy of her paper on Paul Strand in Mexico); and the Center for Media Study at the State University of New York at Buffalo. Also contains a March 1978 Film and Video Makers Travel Sheet; Magic Lantern Cinema calendar and Native Land program notes; Christian Association and International House International Cinema Series 4 calendar and program notes; automobile registration cards; invoices from Hurwitz; and a draft of a letter from Hurwitz to Tillie Olsen.
    - no title (Box C101)
      - [Unsorted correspondence], 1988; undated (Folder 18)
        Includes notes, a letter confirming that Hurwitz's letter has been received by Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan's office, and empty envelopes from the Department of the Army and the FBI.
    - no title (Box C102)
      - [Envelope Labeled: Correspondence -- my early letters to Eddie R. -- copies], 1989 (Folder 3)
        Correspondence with Professor Cary Nelson at the University of Illinois regarding Hurwitz's correspondence with Edwin Rolfe [a.k.a. Solomon Fishman]. Photocopies of Hurwitz's letters to Rolfe dated 1926, 1930, 1937, and 1945, as well as undated letters, are included.
      - [Correspondence, copies of Hurwitz and Rolfe correspondence, notes], 1990 (Folder 4)
        Correspondence with Professor Cary Nelson at the University of Illinois regarding Hurwitz's correspondence with Edwin Rolfe [a.k.a. Solomon Fishman], primarily on the subject of the letters' dates. Photocopies of letters from Hurwitz to Rolfe dated 1926-1930, 1932, 1947, and 1950, are included. Also includes correspondence between Hurwitz and the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade regarding Heart of Spain and the use of material.
      - [Envelope labeled: Peace spots], 1963 (Folder 6)
        Letters to Hurwitz with descriptions and dialog for "peace spots."
      - [Folder labeled: Bank], 1958 (Folder 8)
        Proposal and notes concerning the idea Hurwitz submitted to Chase Manhattan Bank which would allow customers to make saving deposits at grocery stores.
      - [Envelope labeled: Buffalo Media Study material, etc.], 1956-1965 (Folder 16)
        Contrary to the envelope label there are no materials related to the State University of New York at Buffalo's Department of Media Study. Folder contains correspondence regarding the possibility of a Screen Directors International Guild strike; Patterns of a Profession; screening Here at the Waters' Edge;The Museum and the Fury; puppet films; the care of Hurwitz's mother; a film about Albert Einstein; and the "New Age of World Trade" film project for Fortune magazine. Other correspondents include Rosetta Hurwitz; the Little Red School House; the Hollywood Museum regarding prints of Native Land; New York Council of the Radio and Television Director's Guild; dissolution of Lonesome Train Productions, Inc.; Charles Pratt regarding a film titled "New York Island"; Charles Chaplin (from Hurwitz); and Walt Kelly, regarding an adaptation of Pogo.
      - [File pocket labeled: Port. #1 letters ER -- LH], 1926-1931 (Folder 18)
        Correspondence between Hurwitz and Edwin Rolfe [a.k.a. Solomon Fishman].
      - [File pocket labeled: Port. #2 letters ER -- LH], 1926-1949 (Folder 19)
        Correspondence between Hurwitz and Edwin Rolfe [a.k.a. Solomon Fishman]. also includes correspondence with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; flyers and a news bulletin from the S.R.I, Brigadas Internacionales; and a black-and-white photograph of a room from Edwin and Mary Rolfe.
    - no title (Box C103)
      - [Envelope labeled: Evaluation -- mail 1975 to be combed], 1975-1976 (Folder 9)
        Cards, memos, invitations, and other personal correspondence, most addressed to Hurwitz at Kirkland College. Correspondents include Thomas Brandon, Lee Lowenfish, Hazel Strand, and Paul Strand [photocopy].
      - [Envelope labeled: L.H. mail to deal with on Calif. trip], 1976 (Folder 10)
        Correspondents include Russell Campbell, the Royal Film Archive of Belgium, Fred Aronow, Marie Briehl, and Michael Klein. Also includes notes and contact information related to California, and an invitation to the Paul Strand memorial service, with a draft of Hurwitz's response to Hazel Strand.
      - [Pd. bills Kirkland 9/75-1/76], 1975 (Folder 1b)
        Bills, receipts, and other personal and business records, including phone and utility bills, real-estate rental receipts, chemists' invoices, and insurance policy amendments.
      - L.H. mail to deal with (N.Y.U. medical ins.), 1975 (Folder 1e)
        Personal and professional correspondence. Correspondents include Jane Dudley; Filmtronics Labs; Macmillan Films, regarding Victory Films revenue; New York University, regarding medical benefits; and the University Network Corporation.
    - no title (Box C104)
      - [Personal thoughts by Hurwitz], 1974 (Folder 13f)
        Notes on Janet [no last name given] and her relationship with Hurwitz.
      - [Letter to Peggy Lawson], 1971 (Folder 13h)
        Letter to Peggy Lawson in the hospital.
      - Code 226 poems/unsent letters, 1971-1974 (Folder 13j)
        Personal notes, including poems and notes on a dream by Hurwitz. Also includes personal correspondence received and unsent.
      - [Europe trip notebook, personal correspondence, general notes], 1966 (Folder 17a)
        Personal correspondence; notebooks from Europe trip; and to-do lists.
    - no title (Box C105)
      - Memos and correspondence during production --Hart Crane, 1966 (Folder 1r)
        Notes and correspondence related to the production of In Search of Hart Crane, including notes National Educational Network (NET) memos regarding Screen Actors Guild contracts, film narrators, budget, and bookkeeping. Also includes a letter from Hurwitz to Bertrand Russell regarding the formation of an international tribunal to try American war criminals.
    - no title (Box C106)
      - [Personal correspondence, doodle], 1988-1990 (Folder 9)
        Personal correspondence, including an invitation to a screening of Here at the Waters' Edge to benefit the Federation to Preserve the Greenwich Village Waterfront and Great Port. Also includes a doodle of Hurwitz and Robert L. Carringer's résumé.
      - Leo -- late health notes -- letter re: chemo, 1990 (Folder 10)
        Letter regarding Hurwitz's cancer, dictated to Nelly Burlingham; notes on symptoms; and a letter to Dr. Taub regarding Hurwitz's chemotherapy and its effects.
      - [Personal correspondence from Mari Howard Cooper], 1989 (Folder 12)
        Personal correspondence from Mari Howard Cooper. Includes children's doodles.
      - [New York Foundation for the Arts information; personal correspondence], 1989 (Folder 18)
        Personal and professional correspondence, including memos from the New York Foundation for the Arts regarding funding and film festivals, and a screening invitation from the New York Chapter of the National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences.
    - no title (Box C156)
      - [Folder Labeled: Leo T. Hurwitz graduating degree from Harvard University 1930] (Folder 1)
        Hurwitz's college diploma.
      - [Envelope labeled: Harvard University prizes, program of 1930 graduation with Leo's name in it], 1927-1930 (Folder 2)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's time at Harvard, including a greeting to new members of Phi Beta Kappa, scholarship awards, a copy of his diploma, grades, a graduation program, and letters to Hurwitz's father regarding his good performance.
      - Leo -- personal, 1964 (Folder 3)
        Includes a letter from National Educational Television to the Supreme Court of the County of New York requesting Hurwitz to be deferred from jury duty, and correspondence with Melvyn Douglas and his wife regarding their availability to do voice-overs for Essay on Death.
    - no title (Box C158)
      - [Correspondence, notes, "John Brown" notes], 1966; 1983-1986 (Folder 1)
        Includes notes on the "John Brown" script; a letter from Michael Barret regarding a film about Marc Blitzstein; correspondence in Hebrew; an envelope containing scratch notes from Hurwitz's cutting room table; and a notebook with notes on distribution of Dialogue with a Woman Departed. In English and Hebrew.
      - [General notes, "In Search of John Brown" notes, list of films for Europe trips], 1986-1989 (Folder 11)
        Includes general notes about the "John Brown" script; lists of films for Leningrad and a trip to Finland; and notes regarding an untitled project. Also includes a general to-do list and notes on taxes.
      - "Journal" 1987-89 approx., 1988-1990 (Folder 18)
        Includes "In Search of John Brown" outline and notes; personal papers, with poems; a letter draft regarding possible screenings of Hurwitz's films for a series on documentaries; and a hospital receipt.
      - [Unlabeled notes], undated (Folder 29)
        General personal notes.
    - no title (Box C160)
      - [Box labeled: Misc. Leo Stuff], 1975; 1980-1992 (Folder 1)
        Materials include three black-and-white photographs of Hurwitz; a program for the Dutch series "The American Social Documentary Film: The Thirties"; correspondence from the Institute of Contemporary Art in Boston requesting permission to reproduce Hurwitz and Paul Strand's "Tribute to President Roosevelt" mural; letter from Charles Pratt; membership cards and Hurwitz's driver's license; and a bank statement. In English and Dutch.
      - [Box Labeled: Guestbook -- Leo's memorial 3/30/91], 1991 (Folder 2)
        Guestbook from Hurwitz's memorial service, with entries.
      - [Box Labeled: Current -- to be filed L.H. correspondence], 1960; 1964; 1971-1974; 1980-1991 (Folder 4)
        Personal and professional correspondence regarding apartment subleasing; medical bills; poems and letters to Peggy Lawson; funding for "In Search of John Brown"; interview request; Freedom of Information Act requests; and William Alexander's book. Also includes newspaper clippings related and unrelated to Hurwitz; bank statements; stock certificates; Directors Guild of America materials; the draft of 1988 talk Hurwitz gave about the 1968 Columbia protests; drawings; questions about Jane Dudley and dance; campaign flyer for Eleanor Burlingham; certificate for Rosetta Hurwitz's cremation; film revenue reports; and festival flyers.
      - Bills from July '84 prostate operation -- medical, 1984-1985 (Folder 14)
        Breakdown of Hurwitz's medical expenses, and related correspondence
      - [Personal and professional correspondence, clippings], 1970; 1982; 1987; 1989 (Folder 15)
        Includes a draft of a letter written after Joris Ivens' death; newspaper clippings about the death of Sam Brody and Wall Street; proposed amendments to the Directors Guild of America constitution and bylaws; and a personal letter with a color photograph.
      - Doctor bills, 1976-1985 (Folder 17)
        Medical bills, canceled checks, correspondence regarding results, and an explanation of benefits.
      - [Homeowner's policy, empty stationery envelopes], 1988; undated (Folder 19)
        Homeowner's policy and empty Leo Hurwitz and Charles Pratt envelopes.
      - [DGA correspondence, credited service file, Social Security earnings request], 1988 (Folder 20)
        Correspondence regarding the Directors Guild of America's benefits plans.
      - [Personal and professional correspondence], 1966; 1968 (Folder 21)
        Includes lists of screening invitees; draft of a letter about the Columbia University protests; letter from the Internationale Leipziger Dokumentar (in German); fable about the Columbia protest by Gershon Freidlin; correspondence regarding prints of Native Land; lecture requests; and questionnaires regarding Jews in film and dance in film.
      - Landlord 1989 (and 1988), 1988-1989 (Folder 22)
        Includes landlord correspondence, a Department of Housing Preservation and Development form, and a Senior Citizen Rent Increase Exemption pamphlet.
      - IRS -- notice of increased tax 1986 -- also Traum letter, 1989-1991 (Folder 24)
        Correspondence and forms from the Internal Revenue Service and the Directors Guild of America Pension Department. Also includes Hurwitz's 1990 tax return and Hurwitz's data from a sleep disorders clinic.
      - [Résumé, personal correspondence], 1943; ca. 1962 (Folder 25)
        Includes Hurwitz's résumé, comments about Hurwitz and his work, and personal correspondence.
      - Misc. Leo papers, 1988-1992 (Folder 26)
        Includes correspondence from Switzerland regarding an unnamed film and "Leo Hurwitz Album -- Project"; Hurwitz's notes on the effects of his chemotherapy; Folkways royalties statements; notes on trips to Helsinki and Moscow; correspondence from the Paul Strand Archive regarding stills for a book; a copy of "Hurwitz vs. the CIA"; and a rejection letter from Harvard magazine.
      - Miners film project, ca. 1980 (Folder 27)
        Business card from the Freeman United Coal Mining Company, and union membership for Hurwitz in the United Mine Workers of America.
      - Leo: Obituary, condolences, 1991 (Folder 28)
        Includes a clipping Hurwitz's New York Times obituary, and condolence letters to Nell Burlingham and Tom Hurwitz.
      - Dialogue with a Woman Departed, ca. 1971; 1977; 1981; 1989 (Folder 29)